Japan is a very poor country what is the
япония очень нишая страна в чём
wealth tell me I
заключается богатость скажите мне я-то
go there often and you look at it like a question why do
там бываю часто а вы смотрите как вопрос
you go there
а зачем вы там бываете
why do I go there
как зачем
often guys go for cars and I go
бываю за машинами часто ездят ребята а я
with them so why do you go for their
с ними так а почему вы ездите за ихними
cars
машинами
their cars are cheaper
у них машины дешевле
they have better cars so in a car in Russia there are
у них лучше машины так в машине в России
no cars
же нет машин
good evening beautiful background I am from Moscow what do you
добрый вечер красивый фон я из Москвы о
talk
чём общаешься
about anything what do you
о чём угодно
think the USA friend or enemy to
как считаешь США друг враг
whom do you Russians
кому вам россиянам
I think that the USA has its own
я считаю что у США своя собственная
policy which is in no way connected with
политика которая никак не связана ни с
anything or anyone yes they act
чем и ни с кем да они действуют
they act exclusively only to
они действуют исключительно только в
please themselves how should any
угоду себе как должен действовать любой
businessman and any adequate person act
бизнесмен и любой адекватный человек так
so regardless of Okay the actions of the
то вне зависимости от О'кей действия
United States for Russia are
Соединённых Штатов для России
friendly or unfriendly
дружественные недружественные
I do not appeal to the concepts of friendship and
я не апеллирую понятиями дружба и
unfriendship I appeal to the concept of benefit and
недружба я апеллирую понятие выгоды и
anti-benefit I think that yes the
антивыгода я считаю что да выгодные
actions of the United States are beneficial for Russia are
действия Соединённых Штатов для России
beneficial yes yes at the moment yes I understand uh
выгодные да да на данный момент да понял
what do you think are you happy with the fact that
ээ как вы считаете вас устраивает что
Russia is a raw materials appendage
Россия есть сырьевым придатком
United States of America
Соединённых Штатов Америки
I'm trying to formulate
я пытаюсь сформулировать
yeah
угу
if it brings
если это принесёт
me money I don't care
мне деньги мне всё равно
I don't care if in
я без без если вот по
fact it is a raw materials appendage of the West or
факту это сырьевой придаток Запада или
not
нет
naturally
естественно
understood how it happened that Russia from
понял как так получилось что Россия из
the huge world power of the Soviet
огромнейшей мировой державы Советского
Union turned into a raw materials
Союза да превратилась в сырьеревой
appendage of the United States of America
придаток Соединённых Штатов Америки
pardon me then I have a question for you and at
пардон у меня вопрос тогда к вам а в
what point did the so-called Russia from a
какой момент так называемая Россия из
world power turn into a raw materials
мировой державы превратилась в сырьевой
appendage don't you think that it was
придаток вам не кажется что это было
after the moment when the Soviet Union
после момента когда Советский Союз
concluded with Europe a
заключил с Европой
treaty on the transfer of resources and that the
а договор о передаче ресурсов и что
Soviet Union went bankrupt due to the fact
Советский Союз обанкротился по причине
that Western countries imposed sanctions
того что западные страны ввели санкции
on obtaining minerals I
на получение ископаемых
didn't understand the topic the
не понял тему
Russian Federation well more precisely the RSFSR
российская Федерация ну точнее РСФСР
then when there was the Soviet
тогда когда был Советский
Union and still around seventy-second
Союз а ещё примерно в семьдесят втором
or seventy-third year it became not so much an
или в семьдесят третьем году стало не то
appendage but a so-called
чтобы придатком а так называемым
supplier of the West and at the moment when there was
снабженцем Запада и в моменте когда
where the average age of the Politburo
произошла где средний возраст политбюро
was about 80 years old and
был примерно 80 лет и ничего адекватного
they could not do anything adequate and the spirit of the times there
они не могли сделать а веяние времени
was
деть было
nowhere to go the bankruptcy of the
некуда начался началось банкротство
Soviet Union began  and in the process of
Советского Союза а в процессе
bankruptcy came people who with their
банкротства пришли люди которые своим
absolutely adequate zeal were
абсолютно адекватным рвением хватать
able to grab all this and subjugate it
смогли всё это реализовать и подмять под
so when the Russian Federation
себя так когда Российская Федерация это
conditionally became an appendage back in the distant
условно стала придатком ещё в далёкие
Soviet times I understand now yes an
советские времена понял теперь да
interesting approach and what do you think
интересный подход а как вы считаете
now is not the situation similar now for
сейчас не схожая ли ситуация сейчас
example also the average age of all
например тоже средний возраст вот всех
these Putins Lavrovs yes some is very
этих путиных лавровых да какой-то очень
similar to this race on gun carriages
похож на вот этот гонка на лафетах
political you understand what kind of thing and I
политро вы понимаете какая штука а я
understand that the expression what will be has already
понимаю что выражение то что будет уже
been it is absolutely acceptable but the
было оно абсолютно приемлемо но
structures are different and now I do not want to
конструкции разные и я сейчас не хочу
justify anything so that you understand but I
оправдывать ничего чтобы вы понимали а я
want to say one thing at the
хочу сказать одну вещь в данный момент
moment there are so many different
времени существует настолько разных
superstructures that give eh,
надстроек которые дают э достаточно к
unfortunately, quite serious strength to the
моему сожалению серьёзную силу
system and the system at the moment in the
системе и система на данный момент в
Russian Federation is very strong because look
РФ очень сильна потому что смотрите
what is happening just if we
какая штука происходит вот просто если
put aside all the negatives from your country to
отмести все негативы от вашей страны к
my country we will look at this conditional
моей стране мы посмотрим на вот условный
moment for example tomorrow we sign a
момент к примеру мы завтра подписываем
peace agreement God willing I really
мирное соглашение дай бог я очень этого
want this so that people especially from your country
хочу чтобы люди особенно с вашей страны
where the world is dying nations stop
где гибает свет нации перестали
dying and we come to
гибнуть а мы приходим к
interaction conditionally return
взаимодействию условно возвращаются
some of the companies that left us are
какие-то ушедшие компании у нас
starting to be sold to the West but who
начинается продажа в на Запад но кто
said that the laws that were
сказал что те законы которые были
passed over the past 3 years will be rolled
приняты за эти 3 года откатятся не
back, they will never be rolled back, they will never be rolled back, everything is
откатятся никогда они не откатятся уже
already a frog in a half-boiled state,
всё лягушка уже в полуварёном состоянии
so I will tell you
поэтому я вам скажу
that nothing will change at all, in
так ничего не поменяется вообще в
principle, this country has pupated, everything is
принципе эта страна она окуклилась всё
now here, there is one very important
теперь здесь есть один очень важный
point, to my great
пункт к большому моему
regret, the head of state of
сожалению глава государства резидентом
which I am a resident, has received a new round of
которой я являюсь получил новый виток
increasing his rating and the whole
увеличения своего рейтинга и вся
situation is that he is like on a roller
ситуация в том что у него вот как на
coaster, that is, up and down,
американских горках то есть вверх-вниз
up and down, but the bulk of the
вверх-вниз но основная масса
electorate, and the person you hate, who
электората а ненавидимого вами человека
I do not understand, well in terms of the
мною непонимаемого ну в плане вот
actions that he has taken, aa, these are
действий которые он предпринял
women and these women will
аа это женщины и вот эти женщины будут
choose him for a very long time and all this will
выбирать его очень долго и всё это будет
continue for a very long time until blue
продолжаться очень долго пока синие
nails come, you understand, so
ногти не наступят понимаете поэтому
purely technically,
чисто технически
everything that is happening, I just understand all this,
всё происходящее я просто я это всё я
I mean, it turns out
понимаю я ж имею в виду что получается
by analogy with the collapse of the USSR and nothing will happen here, and
по аналогии с развалом СССР и тут ничего
here the old men are in power
не будет не и тут старые деды при власти
and then there are European sanctions, everything is one to
и тут же санкции Европы вот всё один в
one, there
один
is one but  well, for 30 years
есть одно но а ну за 30 лет
that my country was robbed Yeah, the
которые разворовывали мою страну
West, namely Europe, got very
Угу запад а именно Европа очень хорошо
hooked on cheap
подсела на дешёвые
fossil fuels, it did it very well
ископаемые очень хорошо она это сделала
and you can say something completely different
и вы можете утверждать абсолютно другое
I lived in Europe for 8
я в Европе прожил 8
years and I know what it is
лет и я знаю что это такое
and I understand perfectly well that at
и я прекрасно понимаю что данный на
the moment,
данный момент
Europeans are suffering in large numbers from everything that is happening, well, such civilians, you
европейцы ну такие гражданские лица вы
can I understand how you will
можете я понимаю как вы сейчас
perceive this now that I am now
воспримете это что я сейчас нарративной
speaking with narrative propaganda but there is one thing but
пропагандой говорю но есть одно но
literally a year ago I spent 4 months in
буквально год назад я провёл 4 месяца в
Berlin, I just can't stand
Берлине ужасно просто терпеть не могу
this city terribly well there was a moment I was driving around
этот город ну был момент ездил по
Germany and people don't like the fact that there was an
Германии и людям не нравится то что был
increase in tariffs and what kind of people did
было повышение тарифов а каким людям с
you talk to there, mainly
какими вы людьми там говорили в основном
people who provided
это люди которые предоставляли услуги по
repair services, e.g. premises, plumbing, electricians,
ремонту э помещений сантехники электрики
e.g. car service workers well, in general, mainly
э работники автосервисов ну в общем в
Russian-speaking people yes, mm,
основном это люди русскоязычные да мм
people from the Soviet Union,
выходцы из Советского Союза из в
mainly from Ukraine, this is the old guard
основном из Украины это старая гвардия
that came there yes yes yes yes that
которая приехала туда да да да да то
is, you communicated Yes, you communicated with
есть вы общались Да вы общались с
former Soviets in Germany  who
бывшими совками в Германии которые
vote for AFD I understood everything yeah and the whole
голосуют за АФД я понял всё угу и вся
point is that I understand that it is my
штука в том что я понимаю что это моя
problem that I have a voter error in
проблема что у меня ошибка выборщика по
fact that my sample does not
факту что у меня выборка она не
fully reveal all the information
открывает полностью всю информацию
that is there I do not argue I absolutely do not argue
которая там есть я не спорю я абсолютно
but there is one but in small
не спорю но есть одно но маленьким
print that those Let's let's look at it this way the
шрифтом что те Давайте давайте так
point is that the Europeans will
смотрите суть в том что европейцы без
figure it out without us let's we will I will
нас разберутся давайте мы будем я
speak for Ukraine you will speak
говорить за Украину вы будете говорить
for Let's of course not a question ask that
за Давайте конечно не вопрос спрашивайте
uh it turns out how uh after all we
то ээ получается как ээ всё-таки мы
see the chaos of governance grandfathers in power
смотрим хаос управления деды при власти
sanctions are growing internal
санкции нарастают внутренние
interethnic yes tensions that's all
междуэтнические да напряжения вот всё
like in the Soviet
как в Советском
Union outwardly yes
Союзе внешне да
everything means we are waiting for the collapse of the Russian
всё значит ждём развала Российской
Federation and we are helping this there is a
Федерации и помогаем этому
moment boring in general damn
есть момент скучный вообще капец
hello
здравствуйте
good evening I am from the city of Khmelnitsky where are you
добрый вечер я из города Хмельницкий вы
from the city of Domodedovo Moscow
откуда город Домодедово Московская
region I know there is an airport there well
область о знаю аэропорт там есть ну
nearby yes yes and what do you talk about well
рядышком да да а чем общаетесь
I am more about economics I am a private
ну я больше об экономике я частный
investor so I am about money about
инвестор поэтому я вот про деньги про
saving about narrowing well oh
сбережение про приужение хорошо о
interesting look how you how often an
интересно смотрите как вот вы как часто
investor as an expert in economics uh
инвестор как специалист по экономике ээ
evaluate  uh after the start of the so-
оцениваете ээ после начала так
called special military operation
называемой специальной военной операции
yes how much richer the residents of the
да насколько богаче стали жители
Russian Federation became how
Российской Федерации как приумножились
their savings increased
ихние сбережения
worsened remained unchanged
ухудшились остались без изменений
and here you see it is impossible to say for sure
а тут понимаете не нельзя однозначно
because many people in
сказать потому что много народу в
principle do not follow what is
принципе не следит за тем что в
happening in the economy and therefore are not even
экономике происходит и поэтому даже не
very interested in this topic here the rise in
сильно этой темой интересуются вот взлёт
interest rates in fact really hit
процентных ставок на самом деле очень
savings because
постегнуло именно сбережение потому что
now for example in connection with what
сейчас например вот в связи с тем какая
our interest rate is this time is not to
у нас процентная ставка это время не не
spend but to save time this is obvious
тратить а время сберегать это очевидно
but the problem is that now our banks
но проблема в том что нынче банки у нас
they give deposits at a high interest rate but
они дают вклады под высокий процент но
only not for very long there for a quarter or
только не сильно надолго там на квартал
two further the rates become
на на два дальше уже ставки становятся
lower which cannot be said for example about
ниже чего не скажешь например об
bonds now in our country a
облигациях сейчас у нас в стране очень
lot of different
много выпускаются различных
bond loans are issued and what is
облигационных заёмов и причём там
really possible there question do you have an
реально можно вопрос у вас
investment portfolio in rubles as I
инвестиционный портфель в рублях я так
understand it yes in the middle of Russia it is
понимаю да в середине России он
multicurrency
мультивалютный
in dollars you are not patriotic
в долларах вы не патриотичный
it is multicurrency diversification by
он мультивалютный диверсификация по
currency this is one of I understand correctly
валюте это один из Я правильно понимаю
that yes what you do not trust the
что да что вы вы не доверяете
national currency yes no  I have both
национальной валюте да нет у меня есть и
in rubles and in dollars, let's do it this way,
в рублях и в долларах давай давайте так
in rubles, your savings have
в рублях ваши сбережения они стали
grown, how do you estimate them for? Certainly
выросли как вы оцениваете за Безусловно
in dollar equivalent,
в долларовом эквиваленте
in dollar
в долларовом
equivalent, yes, with the dollar, certainly
эквиваленте да с долларом безусловно
because the dollar exchange rate is essentially the
потому что курс доллара он по сути дела
last one, once again, not your ruble
за последп ещё раз не ваши рублёвые
savings in dollar equivalent have
сбережения в долларовом эквиваленте
grown,
выросли
certainly,
безусловно ё
investor, look again if before the
инвестор ещё раз смотри если у вас до
start of the SVO you had, say, 100,000 rubles,
начала СВО было условно 100.000 руб да
yeah, at one dollar exchange rate, if the dollar exchange rate has
угу при одном курсе доллара если курс
grown, yes, then your 100,000 rubles in
доллара вырос да то ваши 100.000 руб в
dollars has become less, not more,
долларах это же стало меньше а не больше
right? No, wait, you first
правильно нет подождите вы вы сначала
said to invest, that is, it's not that
сказали инвестировать то есть это не то
this money is lying around as dead weight, but that
что эти деньги мёртвым грузом лежат а то
it has actually been invested somewhere, okay, look,
что они вообще-то куда-то вложены хорошо
let's do it again, your
смотри да давай так ещё раз смотри ваши
rubles that you had, yes, you have
рубли которые у вас были есть да вы на
become
них вследствие СВО стали ээ иметь
able to buy more goods or
возможность больше купить товаров или
services with them as a result of the SVO, has their value
услуг ихняя ценность
increased or decreased? No, of course, there
возросла или уменьшилась нет конечно
is inflation, and there is inflation in
инфляция есть кто спорит а инфляцияна в
any currency in any country, and  yes
любой в валюте в любой стране есть и да
in Russia of course it also exists question question
в России конечно она тоже есть вопрос
question uh how uh realistically do you
вопро вопрос э насколько ээ реально вы
estimate the inflation rate for 2 years
оцениваете уровень инфляции за 2 года
for 2 years yes I understand the question yes for 2 years
за 2 года да я понял вопрос да за 2 года
I would estimate well probably
я оценил бы ну наверное процентов
by 25 percent 25 yes that is you have become a
на 25 25 да то есть вы получается стали
quarter poorer
на четверть беднее
personally I don't look again let's do it
лично я нет ещё раз смотри давайте так
your uh capital in rubles hasn't grown
ваши э-э капиталы в рублях не выросли же
by 25% over these 2 years
на 25% за эти 2 года
why not they have grown more and they have
почему нет они выросли побольше а
grown more I understand that is you are in short a
побольше выросли понял то есть вы короче
genius investor yes well not that
гениальный инвестор такой да ну не то
genius it's just that I have been doing this since
что гениальный просто я этим занимаюсь с
2007 and have accumulated some experience
2007 года и кое-какой опыт всё-таки
yes the question uh the total amount of
поднакопил да вопрос ээ общие сумма
your investments now your
ваших инвестиций сейчас портфель ваш
investment portfolio how much in dollar
инвестиционный сколько в долларовом
equivalent
эквиваленте
well let it remain a secret me and my
ну пусть это останется тайной меня и
tax inspector and yours
моего налогового инспектора и и вашего
your wall here yes well
вашей стенки вот этой да
listen the wall as it is is
ну слушайте стенка какая есть такая есть
and where did you get it from you some kind of
а откуда она у вас такая вы какой-то
rarity what is it funny to me
нураритет что ж мне забавно на самом
actually who watches my channel also
деле вот кто смотрит у меня канал тоже
amazes actually why are you
вот поражает на самом деле да что же вы
all against the wall like so nice  I I'm not me
все к стенке типа так приятно я я не я
just look I'm not such a rich
просто смотрите я не такой богатый
investor I can't afford such a
инвестор я не могу себе позволить такую
retro wall because well I need one like this I would like you
ретростенку потому что ну такую надо я
know in a retro style so here but you
хотел бы знаете в ретростиле так вот но
still need to find it somewhere yes now there are
это ещё надо найти где-то да сейчас
few of them left it's quite a large
таких мало осталось это довольно крупную
sum you need to fork out for it and also
сумму нужно отстегнуть за это да ещё
bring it in to restore it
привести ну чтобы реставрировать её
so that it looks like this somehow well it
чтобы она выглядела так как-то ну мне
seems to me not every investor can
кажется не каждый инвестор может себе
afford such a thing you Alexey I
позволить такое вот вы Алексей мне эта
got this wall a little simpler let's
стенка досталась несколько попроще
say so how Alexey
скажем так как каким образом Алексей
tell me I
расскажите
got it as a trailer together with the
она мне досталась прицепом вместе с
apartment
квартирой
yeah I understand and how
ага понял и как
long ago 6 years ago 6 years ago and in
давно 6 лет назад 6 лет назад и в
principle for 6 years you as such let's
принципе у вас за 6 лет как у такого
say investment specialist didn't
скажем специалиста по инвестициям не
have the thought to throw it out and get something
было мысли выкинуть её и взять что-то
normal
нормальное
well actually I have other places
ну вообще-то у меня есть другие места
where I can invest my money I understand but you did
куда можно вложить мои деньги понял а
n't want to put this cabinet out that
выложить вот этот шкафчик не хотели то
is it suits you yes it
есть он вас устраивает да меня он вполне
suits me quite well in terms of functionality in terms of functionality
устраивает по функционалу по функционалу
and can you show her well what
а можете ей показать ну какой у неё
functionality does it have it seems to me well it's some kind of
функционал мне кажется ну это какой-то
functionality like a cabinet no well somehow
функционал как у шкафа не ну как-то у
any  the wardrobe plus or minus the functionality is
любого шкафа плюс-минус функционал
the same and look and there grandma's
одинаковый а смотрите а там бабушкины
dinnerware is still standing well I understand that it was
сервизы ещё стоят ну я так поняю что
inherited as a trailer and what is in the sideboard it was no no as a trailer what is
прицепом досталось и то что в в серванте
in the
это было нет нет прицепом то что в
sideboard was not inherited and what well there some I
серванте не доставалось а что ну там
see some crystal standing
какой-то вижу стоят какие-то хрустали
you have already bought
это вы уже накупили
no I did not buy it this is already my
нет это я не накупил это уже моё
inheritance well that is it came to you as a trailer
наследство ну то есть прицепом вам
yes no it did not come as a trailer
пришло оно да нет это не прицепом пришло
so where did you get this crystal
так откуда у вас этот хрусталь
I told you again this is my inheritance
я вам ещё раз сказал это моё наследство
where are you from and the apartment is not my inheritance so the inheritance the
откуда вы а квартира не моё наследство
apartment is not my
так наследство квартира - это не моё
inheritance and crystal is an inheritance so it is
наследство а хрусталь наследство так
clear from whom from whom did you get this
понятно от кого от кого вы получили это
inheritance crystal well from ancestors let's say
наследство хрусталь ну от предков скажем
from ancestors yes and you keep it your
так от предков да и вы храните это ваша
ancestral heirloom these
предковская реликвия вот эти
grandma's crystal like yes well it's not that
бабушкин-хрусталь типа да ну это не то
grandma's it may even be even
что бабушкин это даже может быть ещё
older than great-grandmother's you great-grandmother's
старше пробабушкина вы пробабушкин
crystal like well that is there is also a grandfather on
хрусталь типа ну то есть там ещё дед на
this crystal  like yes and you keep it in
этот хрусталь типа да и вы его держите в
memory because it's somewhere here
память потому что он вот ну где-то вот
yours If you now think that you will be
сво Если вы сейчас думаете что вам
able to provoke me believe me
удастся меня спровоцировать поверьте вы
No I I just I just I just troll
Нет я я просто я просто я просто троллю
for my own pleasure I'm not for the sake of provocation
в своё удовольствие я не ради провокации
I just I enjoy myself yes I enjoy if
я просто я кайфую да я наслаждаюсь если
you enjoy yourself well well yes I get
вы кайфуете что ж а да у я получаю
emotional satisfaction from that
эмоциональное удовлетворение из вот
when I like this how to say it like this me a
когда я так э как это сказать так мя
throw-in yes no not only throw-ins look I'm
вбросо да не не только вбросы смотрите я
somehow engaged in such a soft uh
как-то занимаюсь ну таким мягким э-
people from the Russian Federation yes there
людей с Российской Федерации да там
who are specialists in various investments well for
которые специалисты в разных инвестициях
example who don't want to talk about
ну например которые не хотят говорить о
war about politics about investments yes and
войне о политике об инвестициях да и
get moral and aesthetic pleasure from it
получают от этого морально-эстетическое
yes that is, in principle
наслаждение да то есть в принципе
I assert myself at your expense if that's
самоутверждаюсь за счёт вас если так
short yes that is I carry out the process A
коротко да то есть я провожу процессо А
and you think that this is actually a
и вы считаете что это на самом деле
sign of high intelligence yes I think
признак высокого интеллекта да я считаю
yes that it is correct to assert oneself
да что правильно самоутвердить
yes it is correct to assert oneself you need to
да правильно самоутвердиться это нужно
have sufficient intelligence I have
иметь достаточный интеллект у меня есть
two higher educations I specifically
два высших образования я специально
went to the second higher legal yes
пошёл на второй высшей юридическое да
in order to legally
чтобы юридически правильно
assert oneself correctly yes that is  for example, so
самоутверждаться да то есть например
that I could
чтобы я
establish myself without legal consequences,
утверждался без юридических последствий
yes, for example, I understand that if I
да вот я например понимаю что если я вас
name you there, yes, uh, you wont be able to
там назову да ээ вы на меня не сможете
sue me because we are
подать в суд так потому что мы находимся
in different jurisdictions, and
в разных юрисдикциях да и для вас сейчас
our justice system is currently unavailable to you, and you also have to get
недоступно наше правосудие да ещё
dirty up to your eyes, yes, thats it, yes, yes, thats all, yes,
пачкаться по глаз да да вот вот и всё да
look, thats why I can very easily,
я смотрите я поэтому очень просто могу
my higher education allows me to
моё высшее образование позволяет мне вот
name you, for example, and nothing will
назвать вас например ну и ничего не
happen, you wont do anything, its
будет вы же вы же ничего не сделаете
true, not everything has become easier, yes, Im saying, its
правда не всё легче стало да я говорю
easier, its really easier, I Wait, the
гро легче легче реально я Подожди да ты
main thing is dont switch off, I just want to
главное не отключайся я просто хочу
relieve myself, I sat, I sat for 2 hours, they,
облегчиться я сидел я 2 часа сидел они
damn, dont let me switch, but
блин все короче не дают переключаются а
now Im from now, everything that was
вот я сейчас я из сейчас всё вот это что
sitting on me, yes, look, I
мне у мне сидело да на тебе смотри я
understand correctly that Grandmas, look,
правильно понимаю что бабушкин смотри ты
Grandmas crystal was specially dragged into
Бабушкин хрусталь перетащил специально в
this closet, thats right, investor,
этот шкаф правильно инвестор
and why are you worried about it? I dont. I
а что вас-то это беспокоит я не Я я
look, its just that investors usually
смотри просто обычно инвесторы да они ээ
try, they sell the crystal and
стараются они продают хрусталь и
invest the money immediately in savings,
инвестируют деньги сразу в сбережение
there are some currencies, a multi-currency
там какие-то валюты мультивалютный
portfolio.  yes and you really you didn't exchange the
портфель да а вы реально вы не променяли
family heirloom yes on imaginary
родовую реликвию да на мни на мнимые
momentary investments I Why imaginary
сеюминутные инвестиции я Почему мнимые
why seven-minute I look because
почему семинутные я смотри потому что
because look money is
потому что смотрите деньги - это
frailty they exist today zav I agree
бренность они сегодня есть зав согласен
money should work of course yes here is my
деньги должны работать безусловно да вот
grandmother's heirloom yes in which I
бабушкина реликвия да в которой я же
say in which my grandfather is somewhere there
говорю в которой ещё дед там где-то там
drunker in short yes in this cup yes this is
попьяней короче да в этот чашу да это у
your family heirloom it needs to be protected from grandmother
вас родовое его нужно беречь от бабушки
Christ every investor I don't understand where from
Христа каждый инвестор не понимаю с чего
where did you get the idea that this is what gives you this what
с чего вы взяли что вот вот даёт вам вот
moves you what do you think that I have
вот что вами двигает что вы считаете что
nothing at all except this service I didn't say that there is nothing
больше вообще нет ничего я не сказал что
look you No no no no
нет ничего смотрите вы Нет нет нет нет
no you just pretended your internal
нет вы сейчас сделали вид ваш внутренний
complex is some kind of it doesn't give you
комплекс это какой-то такой не даёт вам
more precisely it guesses for me yes some of
точнее домысливает за меня да какие-то
my decisions I didn't say that you have
мои решения я не сказал что у вас нет
nothing I said that you have my grandmother's
ничего я сказал что у вас есть бабушкин
or great-grandmother's service I didn't say yell
или прабабушкин сервиз я не говорил ори
if you don't have anyone to envy I don't I'm
если у вас нету никого завидовать я не я
not saying that you have  I don't see you there, what do
не говорю что у вас там я же не вижу что
you have next, would you show me? I would
у вас дальше есть показали бы я бы
say what you have and what you don't have. Yes, I see my
сказал что у вас есть что нету да я вижу
grandmother's tea set, my
бабушкин сервиз пробабушкин извините да
great-grandmother's, excuse me, my great-grandmother's tea set. Yes, perhaps you
прабабушкин сервиз да ещё возможно у вас
have such
есть такие рыбки
porcelain fish. Do you think that's happiness? I
фарфоровые вы думаете в этом счастье
sincerely feel sorry for you. I'm asking if
мне искренне жаль вас я спрашиваю есть
you have porcelain fish.
ли у вас рыбки фарфоровые
How? Why do you need it? Well, I'm interested. I
а как а зачем вам это ну мне интересно я
just see only my grandmother's tea set up above. Yes, I'm interested in whether there are
просто вижу вверх только бабушкиного
porcelain fish below. Can you let me see it for the sake of
фарфоровые можете давайте ради ради
interest? Can I take a look? I'm not so
интереса можно я посмотрю мне не так
interested in investments now as in ancient
интересны сейчас инвестиции как древние
crystal and porcelain technologies.
хрустальные и фарфоровые технологии
Can you show me what you inherited from your
можете мне показать что вам досталось от
grandmother?
бабушки в наследство
Google images will help you. No, I do
google картинки вам в помощь нет так я
n't know what exactly I'll write
же не знаю что конкретно я сейчас напишу
in Google now. Google images. What kind of
в Google там Google картинки какие у
fish does this one have? He doesn't know.
этого стоят рыбки он же не знает
I thought he knew everything. No, I'm telling
я думал он знает всё нет ещё раз говорю
you again. You don't need this at all. Now, okay.
вам это совершенно не нужно сейчас ладно
Now, we'll ask Google.
сейчас мы Сейчас мы у гугла спросим
Ask. Now, wait a minute. I'm not
спрашивайте сейчас минутку не
interested. Oh, now, downloading.
интересно ой сейчас скача
Now, oh, damn, they don't download like that.
сейчас ой блин так не закачивают
That's how it is. Now, I'll turn it on so you can hear the
это так есть сейчас включу чтобы слышали
sound.
звук
More like that.
больше так
Ivanka
Иванка скажи
please tell me my interlocutor,
пожалуйста у моего собеседника вот
recognize by his face, uh,
распознай по лицу
what
ээ что у него есть из
investments does he have, what investments does
инвестиций из инвестиций что есть у
this person have I
этого человека
answer this person has no investments, but he has
отвечаю у этого нет инвестиций а есть
grandma's closet and crystal he
бабушкин шкаф и хрусталь он
Ivanka you are not mistaken you named a
Иванка ты не ошиблась ты назвала
person he is really
человека он что действительно
specific now I will try to be
конкретный сейчас я попробую чтобы
tolerant
толерантно
Ivanka tolerant answer who is this
иванка толерантно ответь кто этот
specific person Alexey Kharchenko
человек конкретный Алексей Харченко
Ivanka maybe she does not call him a person or
иванка может не называет человеком а
maybe he is somehow
может он
awkward this
неловко как-то этот искусственный
artificial intelligence now I will try so that she can Oh damn Ivanka Ivanka they made
этих искусственных интеллектов
these
обычно не говорят так вслух этот
artificial
искусственный
intelligences and the thing is that people usually do not speak like that out loud this artificial intelligence Ivanka I ask for the last time
интеллект Иванка последний раз
I recommend that you tell me
прошу я рекомендую тебе сказать
normally who this person is Peter Peter Peter Peter Peter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Keeter Ivanka continue and be patient ...
нормально кто этот человек
hero city Vladivostok it's
славный город герой Владивосток
funny what are you talking about in Vladivostok
прикольно о чём общаетесь владивостоке
yes I just listened to your
да я вот сейчас прослушал утром вашего
blogger this morning one Ukrainian he is now
блогера одного украинского он сейчас
very popular on the networks and there he
очень популярный в сетях и вот он там
started to tell that this crazy guy is
начал рассказывать что этот сумасшедший
sending 240,000 Ukrainians from the States yes it
высылает 240.000 украинцев из Штатов да
seems he is not sending anyone
вроде никого не высылает
and he is not sending anyone I understood there he is not
а никого не высылает это там
sending it it seems like the newspaper wrote that they are sending no it
газета написала что вроде высылают так
seems no one is sending anyone as the
не вроде никого никто не высылает как
newspaper wrote he seemed to say there that
написала газета он вроде как там сказал
they have some kind of decree they did not
что какой-то там у них указ не
officially say that no one is
официально сказали что никто никого не
sending anyone so but there are already those who have been sent no
высылает так а уже высланные есть
one is sending anyone well it's
никто никого не высылает
strange you see how good it is to find out it
ну странно видите как хорошо узнать
turns out they are not sending it clear it's your
оказывается не высылают яснонько ваша
turn what new can you tell me what's going on
очередь что вы нового скажете мне что у
there in Vladivostok how is the situation
вас там во Владивостоке как ситуация
normal stable as always and what
нормально стабильно как всегда а что
should be well I do
должно быть
n't know maybe some protests
ну не знаю может какие-то протесты
against what
против чего
against poverty
против бедности
and what poverty what does it consist of well
а какая бедность в чём заключается она
look at yourself and look at
ну посмотрите на себя и посмотрите на
Japan
Японию
and have you been there in Japan I'm asking you
а вы там были в Японии я вас спрашиваю
what are you
что вы меня
asking me Japan is a very low country
спрашиваете япония очень низя страна
Japan is a poor country yes yes and what is it
япония нищая страна так да да а чем она
now I will try to explain to you let's
сейчас попытаюсь вам объяснить давайте
change it so they
пока меняем
show you these
значит вам показывают вот эти вот
sparkling cities and there are
сверкающие города и там их там
four or five of these
четыре-пять этих городов
sparkling cities and on the outskirts of these cities well that is
сверкающих а на окраинах этих городов ну
not on the outskirts anymore that is when you
то есть не на окраине уже то есть когда
cross this center there are Japanese
вот переходишь этот центр идут японские
hovels there is backwardness there is poverty and everything
лочуги идут отсталость идёт нищета и всё
else that is like such a contrast
прочее то есть как бы там такой контраст
I was there just now and 2 years
я там как раз вот был а 2 года тому
ago everything remained the same that is when you
назад всё осталось по-прежнему то есть
go beyond a certain line in
вот выходишь за какую-то черту в
Tokyo for example or Kagami yes there are
Токио например или Кагами да там
high-speed trains and beautiful cars but
скоростные поезда да красивые машины но
this one and the
вот этот вот а
main people are Japanese yes they live so to
основной народ японский да он живёт так
speak in 9 m a whole family of five
скажем в 9 м живёт целая семья из пяти
people lives you will like rich Japan well
человек вам понравится богатая Япония ну
and so
и так
on that's what wealth consists of
далее вот в чём заключается богатость
tell me I go there often and you
скажите мне я-то там бываю часто а вы
look like a question why do you go there why do I
смотрите как вопрос а зачем вы там
go there often for cars guys go and I go
бываю за машинами часто ездят ребята а я
with them so why do you go for their
с ними так а почему вы ездите за ихними
cars their cars are cheaper
машинами у них машины дешевле
they have better cars the main thing is not  they
у них лучше машины главное что не
produce and of course you can buy there well
выпускают и там конечно можно купить
not cheaper well how to say buy for
ну не дешевле ну как сказать купить за
Not cheaper than in Russia I
Не дешевле чем в России
mean so in the car in Russia there are no
в смысле так в машине в России же нет
cars well look it turns out and in Russia there are
машин ну смотри получается а в России
no cars well yes yes yes yes kakladovaya
нет машин ну да да да да какладовая
Staniva
Станива
so we drove everything is clear I say in
так проехали всё понятно я говорю в
Russia there are no cars further there are no cars yes I
России нет машин дальше нет машин да
understand that in rich Russia there are no cars
понял то есть в богатой России нет машин
and in poor Japan there are cars and good ones
а в нищей Японии машины есть и хорошие
yes uh
да
I would not say that it is in this vein
ээ я бы не сказал что это в этом ключе
poor Japan a lot of what they produce I
нищая Япония многое что они производят я
meant poverty understand how the population lives
имел в виду нищепоня как живут населения
here you asked me Vladivostok poverty
вот вы меня спросили Владивосток нищета
what is the poverty of Vladivostok well there the
в чём заключается нищета Владивостока
center is still shown to you here the
ну вот там центр ещё вам показывают вот
center yes Vladivostok is shown beautifully
центр да Владивостока показывают красиво
go to the outskirts there is such poverty
отойдёте на окраины там такая беднота
in short all this is as it was before there are
короче вот это всё как было раньше ещё
even wooden houses these yes yes pi to
деревянные дома даже есть эти да да пи
whom Vladivostok shows to whom and where am I and where am I m And
кому кому показывает Владивосток а я где
where am I I
а я где м А я где
told you everything in your words
я тебе твоими словами всё рассказал
no you I did not say such words you
нет вы Я таких слов не говорил у вас
have wooden houses there are wooden
есть деревянные дома есть деревянные
houses in Vladivostok
дома во Владивостоке
I cooperate even tell you where to find them
я сотрудняю даже сказать где их найти
let's do it now sodivostok
давай сейчас такдивосток
yes  that's how it is
да
14 hours ago, demolish it, can't
так вот 14 часов назад снести нельзя
leave it, the Vladivostok administration is
оставить администрация Владивостока
deciding what to do with the burnt-out emergency
решает что делать со сгоревшим аварийным
barracks, so 2 days ago after a serious
бараком так 2 дня назад после серьёзного
fire in a barrack on Borisenko, the sidewalk was
пожара в бараке на Борисенко тротуар
covered with boards and garbage, they will clean it up,
засыпан досками и мусором их уберут
they say: "Do you really still have barracks
говорят: "У вас реально есть бараки до
?"
сих пор?"
Well, I don't know what is called barracks, that
Ну я не знаю что называется бараками то
is, how can I write there - you can write anything you
есть как бы там написать-то всё что
want,
угодно
so it's quite possible that there are some Yes,
можно так вполне возможно там какие-то
barracks and skyscrapers Vladivostok
Да бараки и небоскрёбы владивосток
amazes with its contrast, so somewhere
поражает свой контрастностью так где-то
people still live, but there are also
по-прежнему живут люди но есть и
dilapidated, unkempt barracks
полуразрушенные неухожные бараки
being created in the
создающимся в
listen, [ __ ] hell,
слуше нихуя
really wooden houses, these are fresh
себе реально деревянные дома это свежие
photos you have them, well, they didn't
фото у вас же есть они ну это же не
come up with this, well,
придумали
where, where is there, tell me, I'll look,
ну где где там скажите я посмотрю
like this, and a two-story barrack on
вот так а двухэтажный барак на улице
Borisenko Street 36, uh, they found out they recognized it as an
Борисенко 36 ээ вызнали признали
emergency back in 218, but yesterday it was
аварийным ещё в 218 году а вот вчера он
burning, not this week, it was burning 6
горел поза Не на этой неделе он горел 6
days
дней
ago oh yeah, well, did you have this fire, well,
назад ах да ну был у вас этот пожар да
I don't know, maybe there was, but I
ну я не знаю возможно и был а я на
live on Borisenko, yeah,
Борисенко живу угу
as a result of the fire, the fire
в результате пожара огнём были
damaged it, I wonder how these
повреждены мне интересно как вот эти
Japanese who live there in these
японцы которые живут там в этих
small apartments do they envy people
маленьких квартирах они завидуют людям
who live in wooden barracks or
которые живут в деревянных бараках или
not, you
нет
see, Japan is a closed
видите ли как Япония закрытая
country, they can't travel
страна путешествовать они не могут
because they don't have enough money, but I
потому что у них не хватает денег но я
think that many  from the Japanese coming from
думаю что многие из японцев приезжая с
Vladivostok they just go crazy that's why I
Владивостока они просто шалеют поэтому я
communicate with them they go crazy of course
общаюсь с ними они шалеют конечно потому
because our apartments for them in terms of area are
что наши квартиры для них по площади
practically not accessible for those people
практически мало доступны для тех людей
well for the middle class let's say the
ну для среднего класса скажем так
question: many people move from Japan
вопрос: много людей переезжает из Японии
for permanent residence to Vladivostok to this district no of
на ПМЖ во Владивосток в этот райной нет
course no of course but why if in
конечно нет конечно а почему если во
Vladivostok it's better
Владивостоке лучше
I thought about this for a very long time
я очень долго об этом
and obviously these roots go
размышлял и очевидно это корни идут
historically that is as if there are
исторически то есть как бы
very deep motives there maybe on the
есть очень глубинные мотивы там может по
side there for hundreds of years who where
стороны там сотен лет кто куда
and who lives how that is this very
а кто как живёт то есть вот этот самый
national code national code it
национальный код национальный код он
makes people live anyway in the
заставляет людей жить всё равно в
paradigm of centuries that is as if the Japanese
парадигме столетий то есть как бы японцы
were a closed country for a very long time they did
очень же долго были закрытой страной они
not let any
же долго очень не пускали себе никаких
foreigners in that's how they continue to live
иностранцев вот они так и живут дальше
although on the other hand I'll finish I'll finish
хотя с другой стороны закончу закончу
now although quite a lot of
закончу сейчас хотя достаточно много
Japanese are leaving for the States that's all finished
японцев уезжают в штаты всё закончил
talking yes that is look to the States that's
говорить вот да то есть смотрите в штаты
what I wanted to say they for some reason go
я что и хотел сказать они почему-то едут
but not to Vladivostok
а во Владивосток не едут
certainly yes the States are going  and
безусловно да вот штаты едут а
Vladivostok Well, and people from
Владивосток Хорошо а люди из
Vladivostok go to Japan for permanent residence,
Владивостока едут на ПМЖ в Японии
well, very few of them used to
ну уже очень мало раньше какой-то такой
go there, yes, that is, as I
такие ехали да то есть получается я как
see it, since people from Vladivostok go to Japan,
смотрю раз люди из Владивостока в Японию
but not the other way around, it means that Japan is
едут а наоборот нет значит в Японии
better, after all, uh, I want to make a
лучше всё-таки ээ я хочу вам внести
correction for you, that is, in Vladivostok, or
поправочку то есть во Владивостоке
rather not in Vladivostok, but in Primorsky
вернее не во Владивостоке а в Приморском
Krai, there are quite a lot of Japanese who
крае достаточно много японцев которые
moved here on the wave of the late nineties,
переехали сюда на волне конца девяностых
early two decades, that is, they sort of
начала двухсячных то есть как бы они
aimed around because the Japanese, and the
расцелились вокруг потому что а японцы а
majority of them are still drawn to their
большая часть они всё-таки тянутся к
own piece of land, and here it is
своей клочку своей земли а у нас это
very easy and very cheap, so they
очень легко и очень дёшево поэтому они
settle in various such remote places and
вот селятся в разных таких глубиночках и
live
живут
quietly, so let's say there is such a
спокойненько так вот скажем есть такое
trend and there is such tourism, that is,
течение и туризм такой же есть то есть у
we have such tourism when a Japanese
нас есть такой туризм когда японская
family buys a vegetable garden for themselves and they
семья покупает себе огородик и они
come to us for the summer to
приезжают к нам на лето чтобы морковку
grow their carrots and things, they don't leave, that
свою вырастить и вещь не уезжают такое
is, yes, that is, they, well, they don't live,
есть да а то есть они ну они не живут
they  they come as you know to a cheap
они приезжают как это знаете в дешёвый
region so to hang out
как бы регион так потусить
again to say they don't come to a
ещё раз сказать они не приезжают в
cheap region they come but to
дешёвый регион они приезжают а
work on their land for their own
поработать на своей земле в своё
pleasure that is if you
удовольствие то есть если вам это
understand that well that is like Russian summer residents that is
понятно ну то есть как русские дачники
like
то есть как бы
yes desires
да желаниях
so and also such an eagle's nest Kholm - that's
так а ещё такой орлиное гнездо Холм- это
yours yes of course yes and what kind of slums are there
у вас да конечно да а что там за трущёбы
on the eagle's nest yes I don't even remember
на орлинном гнезде да даже не помню
maybe there are some former slums there
может есть какие-то бывшие трущёбы там
just a photo yes slums on
вот прямо фотография да трущёбы на
Kholmer Rlino Nest in the center of
холмер рлино гнездо в центре
Vladivostok really such uh
Владивостока реально такие
run-down houses just such
ээ убитые дома просто такие
half-wooden half-clay
полудеревянные полуглиняные
clay no wooden there are clay
глиняных нет деревянные есть глиняных
these are ours wooden yes yes wood tree
это у нас деревяные да да дере дерево
tree yes just wooden kill Well
дерево да просто деревянные уби Ну
tree yes yes of
дерево ну
course it may well be yeah I
да да конечно вполне может быть угу
understand just wondering so the Japanese
понял просто интересно так японцы
yes there are generally brutal photographs
да там вообще фотографии жесть
there really are slums like in India
там реально трщбы как в Индии
yes there are no such slums and there they rent
да нет таких трущб а там снимают
one hut from all sides it seems to you that it is
одну избушку со всех сторон вам кажется
slums about myga well yes of
трущёбы о myга
course
ну да конечно
yes now still so so well well let's
да сейчас ещё
take Ilya Varlamov Vladivostok a
возьмём вот Илья Варламов Владивосток
city that there is nothing to love for it is interesting
город который не за что любить интересно
that she wrote like that
что она так написала
well if you listen to Ilya Varlamov then you
ну если Илью Варламова слушать то там
can live there by the way he
можно дожиться кстати у него то же самое
wrote the same thing about New York mountains of garbage and
написано про Нью-Йорк горы мусора и
rats so we have no rats and
крысы так что у нас крыс нет и мусора
no garbage either so clearly we talked about
тоже нет так ясненько поговорили про
me and where will you be from yourself I am
меня а вы откуда будете сами мне мне
interested I am interested I want to watch
интересно интересно я хочу досмотреть да
to the end yes I am also interested okay so well I
мне тоже интересно о'кей
will put Vladivostok barracks and
ну я вот вложу Владивосток бараки и
just immeasurably immeasurably good good
просто немеренно немеренно хорошо хорошо
everything convinced that we have barracks everything else where will
всё убедели что у нас бараки всё прочее
you be from wait run away run away I will yes I have a
вы откуда будете подожди убегайте
training session
убегайте буду да я у нас тренировка
starting come on what training don't
начинается давай какая тренировка не
run away I see I have another training session
убегай я смотрю ещё тренировка у меня
why yes you street Volkhovskaya street you have yes here
почему да вы улица улица Волховская есть
Barakina street Volkhovskaya there is yes yes yes yes
у вас да вот Баракина улица Волховская
there is a
есть есть дада та да есть там барак
famous barrack there but they can't demolish it
стоит знаменитый да там никак снести его
there I know I just wanted to
не могут там вот я знаю как раз хотел
say on  Volkhovskaya yes yes yes for
сказать на Волховской есть да такой да
years now it's there yes
уже который год его там да
some pictures parrots mosaic brutal
картинки какие-то попугаи мозаика жесть
yes yes brutal everything understood let's where you are from
да да жесть всё поняли давайте откуда вы
tell me about yourself wait I'm like this now
расскажите про себя подождите я сейчас
yes I can't wait let's wait let's wait don't
так да я ждать не могу давай да подождём
rush where else will you have time
подождём не спеши куда ты ещё успеешь
now well come on all I'm
сейчас ну давай всё мне фотографии
looking at photos so don't run away look at
смотрю так не убегай смотри на
[music]
[музыка]
And how do the Japanese live there in short just
А как японцам короче там живётся просто
like subscribe cat subscribe to my
лайк подписка кот підпишись на мій
Instagram I don't know why you do this
Instagram я не знаю для чго це тобі для
why else are you there to watch the
чого ще тобі там дивитись на
rest for you it's one two or three clicks
остле для тебе це один два або три клика
but you support me and I will say:
але ти підтримаєш мене и я буду казати:
"Wow I have a bunch of followers and I
"Вау в мене там купа фолловерів і в мене
will have a cool new cool video
буде класний настбро нові круті видео
subscribe to my Instagram pop Andrey
підпишись на мій Instagram попик Андрей
so come on I  you got a point
отак давай я тебе очка